Finding Aid for William E. Brown papers, 1923-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William E. Brown papers 1923-1972
Brown, William Ellis, 1896-1970.
85896 Aa 2; AC
Republican mayor of Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1945-1957. The collection consists of topical files on Ann Arbor municipal issues, business records from his real estate and automobile sales ventures, scrapbooks, and photographs
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
11 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
The collection was the gift of Mayor William E. Brown (donor no. 3946 ); additional business materials came from William E. Brown III.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
William E. Brown, Jr. was a successful Ann Arbor Michigan businessman specializing in real estate and automobile sales. From 1945 to 1957, he also served as Republican mayor the city.
The Brown papers have been arranged into the following series: Topical files; Other mayoralty papers (relating primarily to off-street parking); Scrapbooks; Business records; and Photographs. The Topical files are the largest portion of the collection and include correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings, and miscellanea concerning such issues as housing, the new city charter, off-street parking, the new Veterans Administration Hospital, planning for a new city hall, Brown's election campaigns, and the support given by Brown to Albert E. Cobo in his campaign for governor of Michigan in 1956. The scrapbooks, 1945-1962, contain newspaper clippings and other materials relating to his mayoralty.
Subjects:
Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Automobile industry and trade--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Automobile parking.; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Elections--Michigan--1956.; Housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Real estate business--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Republican Party (Mich.); Veterans Administration Hospital (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Brown, William Ellis, 1896-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Common Council.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Garages.; Parking.
Genre Terms:
Architectural drawings.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Topical file
  - 1945-1946
    - A-General (Box 1)
    - Airport (Box 1)
    - Annexation (Box 1)
    - B-General (Box 1)
    - Budget Reports (Box 1)
    - C-General (Box 1)
    - Campaign for Mayor 1945 (Box 1)
    - Civil Defense (Box 1)
    - Communications to Council (Box 1)
    - Congratulatory and Thank You Letters (Box 1)
    - Court House (Civic Center) (Box 1)
    - D-General (Box 1)
    - E-General (Box 1)
    - F-General (Box 2)
    - G-General (Box 2)
    - H-General (Box 2)
    - Housing (Box 2)
    - I-General (Box 2)
    - Insurance (Box 2)
    - Invitations (Box 2)
    - J-General (Box 2)
    - K-General (Box 2)
    - L-General (Box 2)
    - Laird, William (City Attorney) (Box 2)
    - Lucking Suit on Fire Protection (Box 2)
    - M-General (Box 2)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 2)
    - N-General (Box 2)
    - O-General (Box 2)
    - P-General (Box 2)
    - Parking (Box 2)
    - Permission to Use City Property (Box 2)
    - Planning Commission (Box 2)
    - Q-General (Box 2)
    - R-General (Box 2)
    - Relocation of US-12 (Box 2)
    - S-General (Box 2)
    - Salary and Wage Data (Box 2)
    - Sewage and Water (Box 2)
    - State Highway Department (Box 2)
    - T-General (Box 2)
    - Tax Sales (Box 2)
    - Taxes (Box 2)
    - Taxicab Ordinance (Box 2)
    - U-General (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - V-General (Box 2)
    - Veterans Administration Hospital (Box 2)
    - W-General (Box 2)
    - XYZ-General (Box 2)
  - 1947-1948
    - A-General (Box 2)
    - B-General (Box 2)
    - Budget Reports (Box 2)
    - Bus Problem (Box 2)
    - C-General (Box 2)
    - City Charter (Box 2)
    - Communications to Council (Box 2)
    - Congratulatory and Thank You Letters (Box 2)
    - Court House (Civic Center) (Box 2)
    - D-General (Box 2)
    - E-General (Box 2)
    - F-General (Box 2)
    - Foreign Letters (Box 2)
    - Freedom Train (Box 2)
    - G-General (Box 2)
    - Garbage and Rubbish (Box 2)
    - H-General (Box 2)
    - Health Department (Box 2)
    - Housing (Box 2)
    - I-General (Box 2)
    - Invitations (Box 2)
    - I-General (Box 2)
    - K-General (Box 2)
    - L-General (Box 2)
    - M-General (Box 2)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 2)
    - N-General (Box 2)
    - O-General (Box 2)
    - P-General (Box 2)
    - Parking (Box 2)
    - Parks (Box 2)
    - Permission to Use City Property (Box 2)
    - Planning Commission (Box 2)
    - Police (Box 2)
    - Proclamations (Box 2)
    - Public Works Department (Box 2)
    - Q-General (Box 2)
    - R-General (Box 2)
    - S-General (Box 2)
    - Sewage and Water (Box 2)
    - State Highway Department (Box 2)
    - T-General (Box 2)
    - Taxes (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's Report (Box 2)
    - U-General (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan (Box 2)
    - V-General (Box 2)
    - Veteran's Administration Hospital (Box 2)
    - W-Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Wuerfel, Paul (Box 2)
    - XYZ-General (Box 2)
  - 1949-1950
    - A-General (Box 2)
    - Air Force Academy Site (Box 2)
    - Annexation (Box 2)
    - B-General (Box 2)
    - Budget Reports (Box 2)
    - C-General (Box 2)
    - Communications to Council (Box 2)
    - Congratulatory and Thank You Letters (Box 2)
    - Court House (Box 2)
    - D-General (Box 2)
    - E-General (Box 2)
    - F-General (Box 2)
    - G-General (Box 2)
    - Garbage and Rubbish (Box 2)
    - H-General (Box 2)
    - Health Department (Box 2)
    - Hoover Report (Box 2)
    - Housing (Box 2)
    - I-General (Box 2)
    - Invitations (Box 2)
    - J-General (Box 2)
    - K-General (Box 2)
    - L-General (Box 2)
    - M-General (Box 2)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 2)
    - N-General (Box 2)
    - O-General (Box 2)
    - P-General (Box 2)
    - Parking (Box 2)
    - Parking Structure Dedication 1949 (Box 2)
    - Permission to Use City Property (Box 2)
    - Planning Commission (Box 2)
    - Police (Box 2)
    - Proclamations (Box 2)
    - Public Works Department (Box 2)
    - Q-General (Box 3)
    - R-General (Box 3)
    - Pent Control (Box 3)
    - S-General (Box 3)
    - Sandenburgh, George (City Engineer) (Box 3)
    - Selective Service (Box 3)
    - Sewage and Water (Box 3)
    - T-General (Box 3)
    - Treasurer's Report (Box 3)
    - U-General (Box 3)
    - V-General (Box 3)
    - Veteran's Administration Hospital (Box 3)
    - W-General (Box 3)
    - XYZ-General (Box 3)
  - 1951-1952
    - A-General (Box 3)
    - Alger, Fred M (Michigan Secretary of State) (Box 3)
    - B-General (Box 3)
    - Bowser Engineering Company (Box 3)
    - Budget Reports (Box 3)
    - C-General (Box 3)
    - City Charter (Box 3)
    - Civil Defense (Box 3)
    - Communications to Council (Box 3)
    - Congratulatory and Thank You Letters (Box 3)
    - Court House (Box 3)
    - Crusade for Freedom (Box 3)
    - D-General (Box 3)
    - Defense Housing (Box 3)
    - Detroit's 250th Birthday Festival (Box 3)
    - E-General (Box 3)
    - Employment (Box 3)
    - Engineering (Box 3)
    - F-General (Box 3)
    - Fair Grounds Property (Recreation Center) (Box 3)
    - Federal Communications Commission (Box 3)
    - Fire Commission (Box 3)
    - Football Tickets (Box 3)
    - G-General (Box 3)
    - Garbage and Rubbish (Box 3)
    - H-General (Box 3)
    - I-General (Box 3)
    - Insurance (Box 3)
    - Invitations (Box 3)
    - J-General (Box 3)
    - K-General (Box 3)
    - L-General (Box 3)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 3)
    - M-General (Box 3)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Moose Property (Box 3)
    - N-General (Box 3)
    - O-General (Box 3)
    - P-General (Box 3)
    - Parking (Box 3)
    - Parks (Box 3)
    - Permission to use City Property (Box 3)
    - Personal Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Planning Commission (Box 4)
    - Police (Box 4)
    - Price Controls (Box 4)
    - Proclamations (Box 4)
    - Q-General (Box 4)
    - Queen Juliana (Box 4)
    - R-General (Box 4)
    - Rent Control (Box 4)
    - Reports of Commissions (Box 4)
    - Road Projects (US-12 and 23) (Box 4)
    - S-General (Box 4)
    - Sanitary Fill Program (Box 4)
    - Selective Service (Box 4)
    - Sewage and Water (Box 4)
    - Sports and Recreation (Box 4)
    - State Highway Department (Box 4)
    - Street Program (Box 4)
    - T-General (Box 4)
    - Taxes (Box 4)
    - Television Channel (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's Reports (Box 4)
    - U-General (Box 4)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan (Box 4)
    - V-General (Box 4)
    - W-General (Box 4)
    - Willow Run Housing Project (Box 4)
    - XYZ-General (Box 4)
  - 1953-1954
    - A-General (Box 4)
    - Alger, Fred M (Box 4)
    - American Municipal Congress (Box 4)
    - B-General (Box 4)
    - Budget Reports (Box 4)
    - C-General (Box 4)
    - City Charter (Box 4)
    - City Clerk (Box 4)
    - City Hall (Proposed) (Box 4)
    - Communications to Council (Box 4)
    - Congratulatory and Thank You Letters (Box 4)
    - Court House (Box 4)
    - D-General (Box 5)
    - E-General (Box 5)
    - Engineering (Box 5)
    - Exchange of Mayors Day (Box 5)
    - F-General (Box 5)
    - Fair Grounds Property (Box 5)
    - Fire Commission (Box 5)
    - G-General (Box 5)
    - Garbage and Rubbish (Box 5)
    - H-General (Box 5)
    - Health Department (Box 5)
    - Housing (Box 5)
    - I-General (Box 5)
    - Insurance (Box 5)
    - International Municipal Congress 1953 (Box 5)
    - Invitations (Box 5)
    - J-General (Box 5)
    - Junior Chamber of Commerce (Box 5)
    - K-General (Box 5)
    - L-General (Box 5)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 5)
    - M-General (Box 5)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 5)
    - Municipal Golf Course (Box 5)
    - N-General (Box 5)
    - O-General (Box 5)
    - P-General (Box 5)
    - Parking (Box 5)
    - Parks (Box 5)
    - Permission to Use City Property (Box 5)
    - Personal Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Petitions for Mayor (Box 5)
    - Planning Commission (Box 5)
    - Police (Box 5)
    - Proclamations (Box 5)
    - Public Works Department (Box 5)
    - Q-General (Box 5)
    - R-General (Box 5)
    - Road Projects (US-12 and 23) (Box 5)
    - S-General (Box 5)
    - Selective Service (Box 5)
    - Sewage Disposal (Box 5)
    - T-General (Box 5)
    - Toll Roads (Box 5)
    - Treasurer's reports (Box 6)
    - U-General (Box 6)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan (Box 6)
    - V-General (Box 6)
    - Veteran's Administration (Box 6)
    - Vienna Trip (Box 6)
    - W-General (Box 6)
    - Water Department (Box 6)
    - XYZ-General (Box 6)
  - 1955-1956
    - A-General (Box 6)
    - American Municipal Association (Box 6)
    - B-General (Box 6)
    - Budget Reports (Box 6)
    - C-General (Box 6)
    - Capital Improvements Plan (Box 6)
    - City Assessor (Box 6)
    - City Charter (Box 6)
    - City Clerk (Box 6)
    - City Hall (Proposed) (Box 6)
    - Cobo for Governor (Box 6)
    - Communications to Council (Box 6)
    - Congratulatory and Thank You Letters (Box 6)
    - D-General (Box 6)
    - E-General (Box 6)
    - Employment (Box 6)
    - Engineer (City) (Box 6)
    - Exchange of Mayors (Box 6)
    - F-General (Box 6)
    - Fahrner, Jacob (City Attorney) (Box 6)
    - Fairgrounds Property (Recreation Center) (Box 6)
    - Fire Commission (Box 6)
    - G-General (Box 6)
    - H-General (Box 6)
    - Health Department (Box 6)
    - Housing (Box 6)
    - I-General (Box 6)
    - Invitations (Box 6)
    - J-General (Box 6)
    - Junior Chamber of Commerce (Box 6)
    - Juvenile Study Committee (Box 6)
    - K-General (Box 6)
    - L-General (Box 6)
    - Laird, William. (City Attorney) (Box 6)
    - Larcom, Guy C. (City Administrator) (Box 6)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 6)
    - M-General (Box 6)
    - Michigan Municipal League (Box 6)
    - Moore, A.D. (Councilman) (Box 6)
    - N-General (Box 6)
    - Natural Gas (Box 6)
    - O-General (Box 6)
    - P-General (Box 7)
    - Parke-Davis Project (Box 7)
    - Parking (Box 7)
    - Parks (Box 7)
    - Permission to Use City Property (Box 7)
    - Personal Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Proclamations (Box 7)
    - Planning Commission (Box 7)
    - Police (Box 7)
    - Public Works Department (Box 7)
    - Q-General (Box 7)
    - R-General (Box 7)
    - Randall, Norman (Councilman) (Box 7)
    - Retirement Board (Box 7)
    - S-General (Box 7)
    - Selective Service (Box 7)
    - Street Closing (Box 7)
    - T-General (Box 7)
    - Taxes (Box 7)
    - Traffic and Safety Committee (Box 7)
    - Traffic control (Box 7)
    - Treasurers Reports (Box 7)
    - Turnpikes (Toll Roads) (Box 7)
    - U-General (Box 7)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan (Box 7)
    - V-General (Box 7)
    - W-General (Box 7)
    - Water Department (Box 7)
    - XYZ-General (Box 7)
    - Ziegler, Charles M. (Box 7)
  - 1957
    - A-Z-General (Box 7)
    - Bendix Aviation Corporation (Box 7)
    - Bus Situation (Box 7)
    - City Charter (Box 7)
    - City Clerk (Box 7)
    - City Hall (Box 7)
    - Communications to Council (Box 7)
    - Congratulatory and Thank-You Letters (Box 7)
    - Fahrner, Jacob (City Attorney) (Box 7)
    - Hoover Ball Plant (Box 7)
    - Invitations (Box 7)
    - Northwest Development (Box 7)
    - Parking (Box 7)
    - Permission to Use City Property (Box 7)
    - Planning Commission (Box 7)
    - Proclamations (Box 7)
    - State Highway Department (Box 7)
    - Traffic and Safety Committee (Box 7)
    - U.S. Conference of Mayors (Box 7)
    - University of Michigan (Box 7)
- Other mayoralty papers
  - Miscellaneous Material on Off-Street Parking (Box 7)
  - Miscellanea (Box 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - 1945-1951 (Box 8)
  - 1952 (Volume 1)
  - 1953-1955 (Volume 2)
  - 1956-1962 (Volume 3)
- Business records (largely board of directors minutes)
  - Huron Valley Chevrolet, Inc. 1928-1933 (Box 9)
  - Huron Motor Sales, Inc. 1933-1972 (Box 9)
  - Brown and Cress 1925-1929 (Box 10)
  - University Motors, Inc. 1950-1964 (Box 10)
  - Ann Arbor Agency, Inc. 1923-1965 (Box 10)
  - Washington Investment Co. 1946-1969 (Box 10)
  - Huron Acceptance 1939-1966 (Box 11)
  - William E. Brown, Inc. 1967-1971 (Box 11)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (Box 11)
    Photographs illustrative of the city of Ann Arbor's building development during his mayoralty, including photos of a parking structure; also photos of plans for proposed Ann Arbor and Detroit, Michigan, civic complexes